A Finding Aid to the Edmund Quincy papers, 1891-1955, bulk 1935-1955, in the Archives of American Art AAA.quinedmu
Archives of American Art
Edmund Quincy papers
bulk 1935-1955
1891-1955
AAA.quinedmu
Archives of American Art
0.7 Linear feet
The papers of painter Edmund Quincy measure 0.7 linear feet and date from 1891-1955, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1935-1955. In addition to biographical materials, letters, price lists, printed items, and a scrapbook documenting his painting career, Quincy's papers also include family photographs and a scrapbook concerning the political career of his father, Josiah Quincy, Mayor of Boston. Material concerning Quincy's father in some cases predates Quincy's birth. Also included are a diploma and drawings by Quincy.
Quincy, Edmund, 1903-1997
Biographical/Historical note
Edmund Quincy (1903-1997) was a painter who lived and worked in New England and abroad. Born in Biarritz, France, and educated in the United States, Quincy was the descendant of three Boston mayors and related to President John Quincy Adams. He had solo exhibitions in Paris, London, New York, and other American cities. Quincy's work is in the permanent collections of the Grenoble Museum (France), Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, and University of Arizona.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2011 and 2014 by Hirschl & Adler.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter Edmund Quincy measure 0.7 linear feet and date from 1891-1955, with the bulk of materials dated 1935 to 1955. In addition to biographical materials, letters, price lists, printed items, and a scrapbook documenting his painting career, Quincy's papers also include family photographs and a scrapbook concerning the political career of his father, Josiah Quincy, Mayor of Boston. Also included are a diploma and drawings.
Biographical materials include travel documents, student IDs and scattered personal items relating to Quincy and his father. Letters concern exhibitions and the sale of artwork. Quincy's writings are about the process of painting and research on Mexican painters Jose Clemente Orozco and Diego Rivera. Printed material includes items related to exhibitions, newspaper clippings, and publicity materials. The scrapbooks of clippings relating to Mayor Josiah Quincy provides insight into Boston politics during the period 1891-1913. Photographs are of Quincy, family and friends. Artwork consists of sketches and student work. The 2014 addition to the papers includes a diploma and assorted drawings.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in 8 series. Materials are generally arranged by record type and chronologically thereafter.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, circa 1911-1936 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Letters, circa 1942-1946 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1935 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, circa 1935-1943 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1930-1955 (Box 1; 0.1 liner feet)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1891-1947 (Boxes 1-2; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1892-circa 1940s (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 8: Addition to the Edmund Quincy papers, circa 1930s-circa 1950s (Box 2; 0.1 linear feet)
Orozco, José Clemente, 1883-1949; Quincy, Josiah, 1859-1919; Rivera, Diego, 1886-1957; Mayors--Massachusetts--Boston; Painters--Massachusetts--Boston; Photographs; Scrapbooks
- Biographical Materials, circa 1911-1936; Series 1; 1 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Items of note in this series include a draft resume hand written by Quincy, an analysis of Quincy's handwriting, passports and student cards from his studies abroad, and two Josiah Quincy campaign cards, circa 1919.
  - Biographical Materials, 1911-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letters, circa 1942-1946; Series 2; 1 Folders Box 1
  Letters are from galleries including a letter from the Contemporary Arts Center (NY), which advises Quincy that his work has an "old-world-two-or-three decades-back sort of atmosphere."
  - Letters, circa 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Writings, circa 1935; Series 3; 1 Folders Box 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  This series includes a twenty page handwritten draft of an essay on Mexican painter Jose Clemente Orozco. Also found are notes on the painting process that mention glazing and scumbling techniques, referring to specific colors and various effects.
  - Writings, circa 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1935-1943; Series 4; 1 Folders Box 1
  There are two handwritten price lists concerning sales in the New York area and three exhibition price lists from shows at Contemporary Arts (New York), The Art Association of Newport (Rhode Island) and in Sarasota County, Florida.
  - Price Lists, circa 1935-1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Printed Material, 1930-1955; Series 5; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Exhibition materials concern shows in the United States and France. Press releases appear to be from shows at the Contemporary Arts Gallery.
  - Exhibition Materials, 1935-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Phoenix News Publicity Bureau Press Releases, circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1930-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Scrapbooks, 1891-1947; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Edmund Quincy's scrapbook contains biographical summaries and exhibition reviews from major newspapers such as Chicago Sunday Tribune, The New York Times and London Morning Post. There is a black and white photograph of the Quincy painting acquired by the University of Arizona in 1942. A letter from The Museum of Fine Arts in Boston reports interest in Quincy's work in the 1947 "Symphony Show." Other items relate to additional exhibitions of his artwork.
  The "Hon. Josiah Quincy of Boston" scrapbook is annotated and filled with newspaper and magazine articles describing Mayor Quincy's contributions to the city.
  - "Hon Josiah Quincy of Boston", 1891-1913 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Edmund Quincy Scrapbook, 1942-1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Photographs, circa 1892-circa 1940s; Series 7; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  There are black and white photographs of paintings by Quincy and two photographs of exhibition installations. Photographs of people appear to be of Quincy as a young child, Quincy with his father, and as a man in his 20s and 30s. There also are photographs of his mother, Josephine Biamonte Bordighera, other family members, and friends.
  - Artwork, 1927-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Family, circa 1892-circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Family and Friends, 1904-circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Addition to the Edmund Quincy papers, circa 1930s-circa 1950s; Series 8; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  This series consists of a diploma from the Societe Royale Saint Hubert and artwork by Quincy. Artwork inlcudes a few drawings in color; also found are studies of patterns and figure drawings, probably student work since grades appear on some items.
  - Diploma, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Artwork - Figure Drawings, circa 1930s-circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Artwork - Patterns, Still Lifes, Landscapes, circa 1930s-circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Artwork - Drawings, circa 1930s-circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 5)